GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
- The Doc? You know him?
- I know the Doc.
LEE: Sometimes we search
for things we don't wish to find.
I enjoy being the
queen of Gotham.
Glad we understand each other.
There are other ways
for me to hurt you.
HARVEY: Something's
eating at you, Jim.
And you're not gonna feel
clean till you get it off your chest.
That's done now.
I'm at Sofia Falcone's. I
just shot and killed the Pyg.
I see Arkham's
treating you well.
Goodbye, Oswald.
PENGUIN: "I am held captive.
All my brilliance locked away."
- You're still there.
- (LAUGHING)
And you're gonna help
me find a way out of here.
I need a name.
- Ivy Pepper.
- I know Ivy.
SELINA: No, Gordon,
she's changed. Like a lot.
Called Lazarus Water.
LUCIUS: What are
you going to do with it?
IVY: I'm going to
make miracles happen.
You'll reel it in a little, or
should I call your keeper?
- Alfred? He won't answer.
- SELINA: Why?
BRUCE: 'Cause I fired him.
Where's the other
guy who works here?
You mean, Harvey?
He's out sick. You
wanna leave a message?
(CHOMPING)
(SMACKING)
- I do.
- (BURPS)
All right.
What should I say?
Nothing.
Because all of you,
with your blood and your flesh,
and what you will become...
You are the message.
He was a good man.
Doesn't matter that Mario's
gone, you'll always be my sister.
For Falcones, it's
all about family.
I appreciate that.
So, sister to sister...
We're not really here
to look at photographs.
There's only one neighborhood in
Gotham that hasn't bent the knee.
The Narrows has never
submitted to an outside boss.
There's never been someone
like me ruling Gotham.
Okay.
What do you want?
A tax.
Thirty percent on all income coming
from The Narrows, legal and illegal.
Every family there lives
hand to mouth. They'll starve.
We all have to make sacrifices.
I'll need an answer
by the end of the day.
You want me to
kiss the ring? I'll do it.
To keep the peace. But what
you're asking for is impossible.
You'll find a way.
Thought it was all about family.
Never said it was
a happy family.
(DOOR OPENS)
Thank you.
Thank you for meeting me.
My parents' foundation is
having their annual dinner tonight.
I thought we could go.
Somehow, I don't think you
got me all the way down here
to talk about a
fundraiser, did you?
Bruce, what exactly is it
that you want from me?
Help.
Figuring this out. I
can't do it alone, I...
Alfred, I need your help.
No.
What?
Listen, you can't just waltz
back in here and expect me to go
and clean your smalls and cook
your tea. After what you've done.
Alfred, I'm not asking
for that. I've changed.
You have, have you?
It's one thing saying
that you've changed,
and another actually changing.
So show me. Show me how you've
changed, and I might reconsider.
Show you how?
That's for you to
figure out, innit?
I'm asking as a friend.
I'm not your friend.
I was your butler.
And you fired me.
He'll pay for the tea, miss.
Sure hope Lee is gonna
figure something out with Sofia.
Lee being the love
of your life and all.
We're friends.
You know, those koo-koo pills
aren't gonna make me go away.
Well, they have stopped
you from getting out
and trying to kill Lee
again. So works for me.
Mail arrived.
Oh, who's it from?
Oswald.
"I want to apologize...
Can we be friends again?"
What? I'm never
gonna forgive him.
I think it's a nice letter.
- Shut up!
- Hey, Ed.
What has two eyes but can't see?
What has two...
(LAUGHING)
Good lord.
This is new. More aggressive.
The plants are literally
bursting through their flesh.
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
You! Get away from that! Now!
Now.
Same flower growing
out of these bodies.
That's a weapon?
Gordon, this must be what
Ivy did with the Lazarus Water.
Used it to increase the
potency of a toxic plant.
- The seeds made it airborne...
- GORDON: Where's Bullock?
- What?
- He works here.
Harvey killed Ivy's father.
Too late.
No, we're not.
Hey.
Hey!
Damn it, Jim!
Jim, what the hell?
Hey, someone's
paying for that door!
Ivy Pepper.
- Who?
- Mario Pepper's kid.
She's been working
on some biotech.
She attacked your bar.
It's bad.
Donnie, the bartender...
I'm sorry.
Oh, God!
Look, I gotta think
that you were the target.
Jim, I only shot Ivy Pepper's dad
because I was saving your stupid eye.
You can't put this on me.
- I'm not putting it on you.
- ALVAREZ: Guys.
We have decided
to share the footage.
So in a moment the video
we are about to show you
is from a tape
received this morning.
And again, let me warn you.
It is very disturbing.
Plants love us.
They give us food, shelter,
the very air we breathe.
But what do we do in return?
Kill them. Because
that's our nature.
We cause pain.
Everyone I've known has
only hurt or betrayed me.
Maybe I've always known in
my heart what I needed to do.
But I finally have
the power to do so.
I'm giving your city
back to the plants.
Starting with the
people who hurt me.
So if that's you,
your time is coming.
- Guess we know what she's up to.
- Yeah.
She's gonna kill
everyone in Gotham.
Starting with me.
WOMAN: Preliminary reports indicate
that similar tapes have been delivered
to multiple news organizations.
Wait a minute.
What's that there?
HARVEY: Sully's Eatery.
That's in Ives Square.
House must be right across.
You should go to the precinct.
Hey, I'm not hiding like some
freaking coward. All right?
Four people are dead
because she wanted me.
Okay, then we'll work on it
together. You can wear the badge.
Get this straight, Jim. I ain't
working for you now or ever.
I got more contacts in The
Narrows than any of you.
I'm gonna find her. Alone.
Once I find my pants.
LEE: Doesn't make any sense.
There's no money here.
Okay, so it's about power.
I offered to bend the knee.
She's asking for something
she knew I couldn't give.
She wants...
She wants to punish me.
For what?
I don't know. But you
can't fight an enemy
whose motivations you
don't understand, Lee.
You are the greatest
spies in all of Gotham.
You have eyes and
ears everywhere.
The survival of The
Narrows depends upon you.
Whoever learns why Sofia Falcone
wants to destroy Lee Thompkins
will receive a complete
set of encyclopedias.
Minus the T.
Plus 20 bucks.
- Yes!
- Yeah!
Go get 'em.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
OFFICER: We're moving, clear.
She wasn't bluffing.
With this many plants, she could kill
hundreds if not thousands of people.
Search the other room for any
signs of where she's heading.
What are you gonna do to her?
- Where is she?
- I don't know.
I just saw the news.
She killed four
more people today.
You knew where she was
staying. If you had told me,
- we could've saved lives.
- Or not.
I mean, you couldn't even stop
her from hypnotizing your own cops.
So why did you come here?
To try to reason with her.
Have you heard a word
she said? She's a fanatic.
She's my friend.
What do you expect me to do?
She contacts you again, call me.
I'll try and find her,
and bring her in quietly.
Otherwise, stay out of her way.
Harvey?
Hey, I got a lead.
Great.
HARVEY: I knocked some heads.
Heard a hot redhead was poking
around in that dive bar next door.
That is the place in The
Narrows for low-end muscle.
So I figured, if she was
planning something big,
she might've gone
there to recruit.
That's the back entrance.
That's where my
contact said that...
(DOOR OPENS)
Hello, Detective Gordon.
On the ground.
Now. Harvey, call it in.
She's beautiful,
don't you think, Jim?
Drop your weapon.
(WHISTLES)
You don't look good.
I think you might be exceeding
your recommended dosage.
Are you experiencing
"trembling extremities"?
Check. "Cognitive
impairment"? Definite check.
Though to be fair,
how would you know?
Shut up!
Take all the pills you want,
Ed. I'm only getting stronger.
Soon I'm gonna be
out, and the fun begins.
No. I won't let you. 'Cause
I know what you'll do.
Oh, you mean kill Lee?
Yeah, I guess I will do
that. And you can't stop me.
There are things that I can do.
Like what? You
need to face it, pal.
The only way you'll get
rid of me is to kill yourself.
I guess you are smarter than me.
- You wouldn't actually...
- Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
I said drop the gun, Jim.
Do you believe in
fate, Detective Gordon?
I went out today to test my plants
on the man who shot my father.
He wasn't there.
That's disappointing.
Then he found me.
And I realized I could make
him deliver his partner as well.
Fate.
Stay strong, Harvey.
She's controlling you.
I kinda like it, Jim.
Sweet surrender.
GORDON: You need help, Ivy.
Let me find Selina.
She wants to help.
Quiet.
I have to go.
Big plans tonight.
Lots of people to kill.
- Detective Bullock?
- Ma'am.
After you kill your partner, be sure
to shoot yourself in the head, okay?
Copy that.
(IVY HUMMING)
(DOOR CLOSES)
Harvey...
Don't even try and
talk your way out of this.
I wouldn't. But, quick question.
Is Ivy's hair more
auburn or scarlet?
I, uh...
That's a good...
(GUNSHOTS)
(GUN CLICKING)
You think I didn't
come prepared, huh?
You always underestimate me.
That's not why I'm shooting you.
I just think we should,
uh, clear the air.
What do you wanna
talk about? I'm all ears.
How you stole
my job for starters.
GORDON: Was it
really your job, though?
I mean, you only got it
'cause one captain died
and the other one went nuts.
Like hell!
I paid my dues! I earned
that job, and you took it!
You mean like the time
you gut-shot Officer Patel?
That was a mistake.
GORDON: Hey, give
yourself some credit.
You did shoot her
from across the room.
Although you couldn't
face her later, remember?
You didn't have the courage to
meet her the next day, did you?
- You coward.
- Screw you!
(GUNSHOTS)
- We're not open.
- I wanted to see you.
Why? Because you weren't big
enough of an ass the last time I saw you?
- Selina...
- I don't have time for this, Bruce.
Something happened.
- I need to talk to someone.
- Okay, then go find Alfred.
Oh...
You did, and he wanted
nothing to do with you.
Smart guy, Alfred.
- Can you at least hear me out?
- No, Bruce.
Because Ivy's out
there killing people
and I need to find
her and stop her.
So whatever problem you
have going on right now,
you need to figure it out.
I mean, say sorry to Alfred.
'Cause I'm sure whatever
happened was your fault.
According to my spies,
Sofia and Jim were
carrying out an affair
till Jim ended it.
So, technically,
your ex has been sleeping with
your dead husband's mafiosa sister...
Okay, I get it.
If Sofia was sleeping with
the captain of the GCPD,
it was a power
play. And it failed.
I'm her next step.
Why don't I just give
her what she wants?
Power over Jim Gordon.
You would do that?
I'm not trying to get back at
Jim, though he deserves it.
My job is to make sure that the
people of The Narrows are safe.
And I will do everything
in my power to ensure that.
What?
Lee, I...
I have to leave.
- Harvey. Harvey, come on, buddy.
- Where am I?
You were hypnotized.
I need you to focus.
Did Ivy give you any clue
about who she's targeting next?
I can't believe I
let her get to me.
Hey, you wanna help? Here's
how. Did she say anything?
Something about, "They
get rich by murdering plants."
So she's targeting a
group of rich people.
At her place, she was trying
on fancy clothes, fancy shoes.
A party?
She said she had big
plans, couldn't be late.
- Yeah, black tie.
- No, no, no, come on.
Fancy schmancy, like a
charity for hobos or something.
Wayne Foundation's
annual dinner is tonight
over at Gotham Square.
All right. Get the strike force.
I want full body armor, gas
masks, nonlethal rounds.
To fight plants?
When Ivy got me, she was
hypnotizing a bunch of low-end muscle.
Go.
We could really
use you there, Harv.
Jim, she got in my head.
I really... I just don't
trust myself right now.
All right, you can help
out here. Man the phones.
Hey, Jim.
I spent too long
putting this all on you.
What happened between us.
The fact is I only
got myself to blame.
I'll call.
(CLASSICAL MUSIC PLAYING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
And now, ladies and gentleman,
please welcome to the
stage our host Bruce Wayne.
(APPLAUSE)
Good evening.
Welcome to the
third annual dinner
for the Thomas and
Martha Wayne Foundation.
This year we
disbursed $4 million...
Um...
We disbursed $4
million and, uh...
My parents spent their
lives helping people.
I was so proud of them, and I
always wanted them to be proud of me.
And then I saw
them get murdered.
I survived because someone
in my life kept me going.
He's been everything to me.
A teacher,
a protector.
He's been a father to me.
I hope...
I hope he can see that.
And give me another chance.
Thank you.
(APPLAUDING)
That meant a great deal.
But I can't help you.
Not until you accept
who you really are.
I know who I am, I've
seen what's inside of me.
Darkness and anger?
But what's beneath that?
It's a heart that feels pain.
Your heart is what makes
you want to help other people.
Your heart is your strength.
Deny the darkness
and you deny that.
But accepting that is something
that you must do on your own.
Do you understand me?
I was stupid for reaching out.
WOMAN: That was quite a speech.
Hello all.
I'm Ivy Pepper.
- (CROWD GASPS)
- No, no, no, please.
Stay seated.
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
RIDDLER: Can I just say?
This is crazy!
Well, this whole thing
was your idea.
And you're the smart
one, as you always tell me.
Very funny.
Okay, fine! Fine!
You win!
- What?
- You win.
You beat me. Is that
what you wanna hear?
That is very nice.
But I still have to do it.
Wait! Wait!
Wait! What if there's a way
to do this where
nobody gets hurt?
I don't believe you.
So you're just going to kill
yourself without hearing me out?
I'm telling you, Ed.
There is a way to save
Lee without killing yourself.
Or killing us.
I'm listening.
Aren't these crimson
flowers lovely?
You're a handsome man.
But you want more from life.
I can feel it.
(CHOKING)
Bruce, is Ivy Pepper in there?
BRUCE: Ivy?
No, I didn't see her.
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
Get out of here.
Let's go!
GORDON: Breach that door.
We
Are going to turn this room
into the most gorgeous
garden the world has ever seen.
All you have to do
is take a deep breath.
Oh,
a volunteer.
- (CURTAINS RUSTLING)
- (GRUNTS)
GCPD!
Drop your guns.
On the ground, now!
Kill everyone.
- (GUNSHOTS)
- (SCREAMING)
You got this, I'm
going after Ivy.
(ELECTRICAL BUZZING)
(GRUNTING)
I'm getting you out of
here. Come on, let's go.
Listen, listen.
People need your help.
This is who you are.
MAN: Watch the door.
I'm gonna go look for him.
Where'd you go, punk? You
can run, but you can't hide.
(GRUNTING)
GORDON: Hey! Hey!
- Drop it!
- No!
(GASPING)
Hey. Hey.
(SIREN WAILING)
(HELICOPTER HOVERING)
SELINA: You hear the news?
"Crazy Ivy Pepper attacks
the Wayne Foundation dinner."
I'll be honest. The evening didn't
turn out quite the way I'd hoped.
(SCOFFS)
You mean you didn't get
to kill everyone in there?
Something like that.
You got out.
Made it back here.
You always were the survivor.
No, you taught me that, Selina.
What's in the bag, Ivy?
It's the last of
the Lazarus Water
I stole from Wayne Enterprises.
So you can go
and make more
plants to kill people?
Yeah, that ain't gonna happen.
Are you gonna stop me, Selina?
You're gonna remind me
of the old days?
- Tell me I'm not this person?
- (CHUCKLES)
No, I think we're
past words now.
(GROANS)
Well,
Selina Kyle
turns out to be the hero.
I'm no hero.
(GRUNTING)
One scratch is
all it takes, Selina.
And there's no
antidote this time.
And there's no more
jumping across rooftops
for little dead Selina.
I'll keep that in mind.
You're gonna have
to fight me, Selina.
You can't run forever.
I wasn't running. (PANTING)
I was getting this.
This is what you're gonna use
to make all your little plants?
So, I guess it's safe to
say that I shouldn't drop it.
Stop, Selina.
I will let you leave.
Let me?
(SNORTS)
You're not gonna turn me
into some geranium-type thing?
That's so generous.
No!
How can you side with them?
All the people who hurt us.
You think they're innocent?
They're guilty.
Every person in this city,
they spew out poison.
How are you not choking on it?
The only thing that I'm
choking on, Ivy, is your insanity.
(GRUNTS)
You shouldn't have done that.
Now, you're gonna die.
Ivy, look down.
- Well?
- Yeah.
So, what happens
now? We kill each other?
That's an option.
You always did think
you were better than me.
That's not true. I
was your friend.
We were friends, Ivy.
You said so yourself.
That was a long time ago.
I'm a different person now.
This isn't what I want.
Don't get in my way again.
MAN: Lift your hands
up. Got any weapons?
I'd almost think this wasn't
going to be a friendly conversation.
Just being careful.
- They're clean.
- Okay.
Smart lady.
So, you said you wanted 30%
of everything in The Narrows?
What if I told you I had
something more valuable to offer?
Such as?
Jim Gordon.
I know crimes he's
committed no one else does.
It would give you
control over him.
Surely that's worth
more than 30% of this.
I have my own
dirt on Jim Gordon.
But you can't use it.
Otherwise, you wouldn't be
sitting there threatening me,
would you?
Sofia?
Take my deal.
I have a better way to
bring Gordon around.
- (GROANS)
- No! No!
Stay with me, stay with me.
(SCREAMS)
You're never gonna
get out of here alive.
My people are going to kill you.
Your people? Who do you
think planted these guns?
You can come out.
How you doing, Doc?
(SAMPSON LAUGHS)
I'm having Sampson
run The Narrows.
You should have killed me
when you had the chance.
The fact that you didn't told
me everything I needed to know.
(LEE GRUNTING)
Since we're family, I'm
only going to do one hand.
(SCREAMS VIOLENTLY)
SOFIA: Throw her on the streets.
(HAMMER CLATTERING)
Let The Narrows see their queen.
(LEE WHIMPERING)
REPORTER: The scene here
remains largely under control,
but Ivy Pepper remains at large.
Now inside we have a
team of investigators...
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(CELL PHONE VIBRATING)
Yeah.
What?
Where is she?
Sir?
Excuse me?
Are you family?
I'm a cop.
She wouldn't tell us who did it.
She doesn't have to.
(ALARM BUZZING)
Arkham doesn't
get many volunteers.
You do know who I am, right?
Criminally insane
pretty much covers it.
Read.
And sign.
I'll be back.
I hate that you
were right about this.
But it'll keep her safe.
Hey, Ed?
What has two eyes but can't see?
(SIGHS) This again.
Two needles.
Half of Mississippi, who cares?
You should, Ed.
(DOOR BUZZING AND OPENING)
I knew you'd come.
I knew you'd
understand my letter.
How did you know I'd be...
What are you talking about?
I'm not talking to you, Ed.
I'm talking to him.
(LAUGHS)
He read my letter.
Read the first word
of each sentence.
"Please bring Ed to
Arkham, so I can set you free."
What has two eyes,
but can't see what's
happening in front of him.
- Ed Nygma!
- No.
I came here to save Lee.
He read my letter.
You...
You're wrong!
I am Ed!
Edward Nygma, that is it!
Lee believes in me. She
sees me for who I am.
But I see him,
- Ed.
- No.
Lee Thompkins may
have made Ed strong,
but I see the other you.
One whose name I wouldn't speak.
But because he has earned it
and because I need him,
- I'm saying now.
- No!
- Please, please don't.
- I need you.
Please...
Riddler.
(GASPING)
Shall we get to work?
(BOTH LAUGHING)
So?
How'd you make
it off the roof then?
A fire escape on
the next building.
Why'd you run from Gordon?
I mean, you could've
told him, it was you.
I don't know.
I just couldn't.
I'm going to help
people, Alfred.
And if that means accepting
every part of myself, good and bad,
then I will.
I do.
It's what my parents
would've wanted.
Your parents would've
been very proud of you.
I'm proud of you.
Alfred?
If you'd
need a ride back to
Gotham, I can drive you.
I'm not going anywhere, sir.
I'm home.
Congratulations.
I heard you saved the day.
Good job.
There's a reason
you're captain and I'm a
50-year-old screwup,
pouring shots for barflies.
There's a reason, all right,
but it's not what you think.
I screwed up, Harv.
I screwed up bad.
And I'm gonna need
your help to make it right.
Sofia hired the Pyg.
And I knew.
I knew...
And I covered it up.
And now, I'm gonna
take her down.